<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <author>Der von Kürenberg</author>
        <title ana="main">Ich zôch mir einen valken</title>
        <title ana="sub">Text</title>
    </teiHeader>
    <body>
        <head>
            <author>Der von Kürenberg</author>
            <title>Ich zôch mir einen valken</title>
        </head>
        <text>
            <div ana="Text">
                <lg n="1">
                    <l n="1">Ich zôch mir einen valken mêre danne ein jâr.</l>
                    <l n="2">dô ich in gezamete, als ich in wolte hân,</l>
                    <l n="3">und ich im sîn gevidere mit golde wol bewant,</l>
                    <l n="4">er huop sich ûf vil hohe und vlouc in anderiu lant.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="2">
                    <l n="1">Sît sach ich den valken schône vliegen,</l>
                    <l n="2">er vuorte an sînem vuoze sîdîne riemen,</l>
                    <l n="3">und was im sîn gevidere alrôt guldîn.</l>
                    <l n="4">got sende sî zesamene, die gelieb wellen gerne sîn!</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div ana="Übersetzung">
                <lg n="1">
                    <l n="1">I brought up a falcon for more than a year.</l>
                    <l n="2">When I had him tamed as I wanted</l>
                    <l n="3">And when I had adorned his feathers with gold,</l>
                    <l n="4">He raised himself up high and flew to another land.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="2">
                    <l n="1">Since then I have seen the falcon flying:</l>
                    <l n="2">He was wearing silken jesses on his feet,</l>
                    <l n="3">And his feathers were all red-gold.</l>
                    <l n="4">May God bring together those who want to love each other!</l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div ana="Comment">
                <p>Kürenberger's <i>Falkenlied</i> is part of a longer sequence of 13 stanzas preserved only in the Manesse-Codex; they could all form a thematic sequence, but the relationship between the other stanzas is not as strong and clear as in these two. It is not said, whether the voice belongs to a man or a woman, but the association of the falcon with masculine hunting and even love-hunting suggests that it is woman who speaks.</p>
            </div>
        </text>
        <div>
            
        </div>
    </body>
</TEI>

